<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Joshua's resolution; or the duties of houshold-governours discoursed of, and fairly stated; their failures therein mildly consider'd, and without favour or affection impartially weighed. The subject suited to the capacities of tamworth auditory, and preached there, and elsewhere, by John Wagstaffe, A.M. and rector of Little Wenlock, in Shropshire.</title>
            <author>Wagstaffe, John, rector of Little Wenlock.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96416</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W199B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186141</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896045</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896045</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153724</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96416)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153724)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2375:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Joshua's resolution; or the duties of houshold-governours discoursed of, and fairly stated; their failures therein mildly consider'd, and without favour or affection impartially weighed. The subject suited to the capacities of tamworth auditory, and preached there, and elsewhere, by John Wagstaffe, A.M. and rector of Little Wenlock, in Shropshire.</title>
                  <author>Wagstaffe, John, rector of Little Wenlock.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Thomas Snowden; and are to be sold by Henry Mortlack at the Phænix in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Running title: The duties of governours, and their failures therein consider'd.</note>
                  <note>Identifies as Wing W199B, reel 2375, of the UMI microfilm set "Early English books 1641-1700".</note>
                  <note>Cf. Wing W199B which has "Mortlock" in the imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious education --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153724:1"/>
            <p>JOSHUA'S RESOLUTION; Or the DUTIES of Houſhold-Governours, Diſcourſed of, and fairly ſtated; Their Failures therein mildly conſider'd, and without favour or affection impartially weighed.</p>
            <p>The Subject ſuited to the Capacities of <hi>Tamworth</hi> Auditory, and Preached there, and elſewhere,</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Wagſtaffe,</hi> A. M.</p>
            <p>And Rector of Little <hi>Wenlock,</hi> in <hi>Shropſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Sep.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. ſaith King <hi>Solomon</hi> in his <hi>Proverbs, ch.</hi> 24.26. He will be befriended <hi>(not frowned on)</hi> that declares the Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Snowden;</hi> And are to be ſold by <hi>Henry Mortlack</hi> at the <hi>Phaenix</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153724:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153724:2"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle Dedicatory: To Religious, Conſcientious Governours, of all Ranks and Degrees among us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">To the Meaneſt, as well as to the Greateſt.</head>
            <p>NO Preſent too great for ſo worthy Patrons, <hi>(and in particular to my own, and that Loyal one, where it was firſt Preacht)</hi> yet, ſuch as I have, with all heartineſs I humbly preſent to you, you who experimentally know how far eaſier it is to obey, than command. Tho it be a Parents Prerogative to command his Children, yet it is duty in him to obey a Father or a Magiſtrate, place't in Authority over him, tho it be a Magiſtrates Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to controul, and call to account, all under his Juriſdiction, yet it is his bounden Duty to obey Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, and Kingly Government; and tho it be the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt Jewel, and the very Diadem of a Crowned King to
<pb facs="tcp:153724:3"/>command his Subjects, yet it is his Intereſt, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Happineſs to obey his Maker and Creator, that moſt glorious Majeſty of Earth and Heaven<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 8.15.</note>, that you may eaſily obſerve, that no Mortal, no not the greateſt Grandee, but a Deity himſelf<note n="*" place="margin">21.1.</note> that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted (one time or other) from obeying and ſerving as well as commanding and ruling; Therefore what's offered you in theſe following ſheets, 'tis to pleaſure <hi>(Friends)</hi> the befrienders of Godlineſs and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, of Proteſtantiſm and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 2.</note>, and not at all to pretend to inform the Nation of any thing that it knows not, but to remember them that are in it, that they do what they know. It is true, the Land abounds in Knowledge, I wiſh I could ſay the ſame, for the honour of it, that it did ſo too in practice, then we ſhould be as happy<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 13.17.</note>, and as flouriſhing as now we begin to be declining, and contemptible, but that poor <hi>England</hi> may redeem its loſt Reputation, let each of us diſcharge thoſe particular Duties that are incumbent on us; and every ſingle perſon take their own parts that are allotted them; and that their own Conſciences carve out for them, and not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench upon anothers right, that all of us may act and do like Rational men that have Immortal Souls to ſave, like the true Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, like thoſe that do heartily proteſt againſt Rebellion and Popery, Faction and Phanaticiſm, Enthuſiaſm and Atheiſm; nay, againſt Irreligion, and all manner of Prophaneneſs whatſoever, and not to look one way, and with all might and main to row another; for we had not been hitherto ſpared, if kind Providence had not ſtept in between, and watcht over us for good, ſafeguarded us one time after another, from
<pb facs="tcp:153724:3"/>thoſe apparent dangers wherewith we were compaſſed, that we our ſelves do now plain enough ſee; we had ere now been engag'd, imbroil'd in another Civil War, our Hands and Garments by this time, to have been dyed in each others Blood, which would have been ſmall Credit to Chriſtians, or to our Engliſh Nation *.</p>
            <p>But if after all, there be only a ſhew of Sanctity, a meer ſhadow and Mock-pageantry of Piety, and that the Subſtance and Glory is wanting, <hi>viz.</hi> (the practice) have we not ſtill great cauſe greatly to fear (that under the colour of Religion, which it utterly diſowns) of having the old abhorr'd Tragedy ſham'd upon us afreſh, if it were not for the prudent Conduct and Mercifulneſs of one of the moſt indulgent Princes that did ever ſway a Royal Sceptor, that I hope will yet vanquiſh the bittereſt of his Enemies, by the wonders of his kindneſs and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 19.11, 12.</note>, that ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been hitherto already ſtretcht out to a miracle, that if we at any time miſcarry, it will ſoon be found, detected, to be our diſſervice, untowardneſs, diſobedience, ingratitude to Powers. Ordained of God<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note>, <hi>(to God-like Clemency and Authority)</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we ſtill perſiſt in our diſingenuity, inhumanity, to put him upon any thing which his Kingly Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence cannot yield to<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 14.23.</note>; and for all that, what do we do more by our Jealouſies and Whiſpers<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 16.28, 29, 30.</note>, but ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to treſpaſs, dun and harraſs the Lords Anointed<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 24.6.</note>? and then what do we do leſs but dare Majeſty it ſelf at length to puniſh us, and provoke him to that which he is loth to undertake, <hi>viz. (our Ruine)</hi> yet if we periſh, (<hi>if we periſh</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Eſther 4.</note>) whom have we to blame but our ſelves?</p>
            <p>And to me 'tis as clear as noon-day Light, that the wickedneſs, ungovernableneſs, hate and haughtineſs of the Peoples Spirits does ſtrangely portend, if not
<pb facs="tcp:153724:4"/>timely prevented, our miſery and downfall, which that ſo dreadful a ſtorm<note n="*" place="margin">Jonah 1.</note> may be diverted, and rather lighten on the Proteſtant Foes, I am not ſhy in own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf one of that Loyal Praying number<note n="*" place="margin">3.10</note> 
               <hi>(thô Prayers and Tears, by ſome, are made light of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready;)</hi> That is, an humble Petitioner at the Footſtool of Heaven, where it is no crime to be a Supplicant, tho one of the meaneſt, yet willingly would be one of the Humbleſt, Trueſt Servants</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>To the GREAT JEHOVAH, And to all his Vicegerents here below, (To the</hi> Pater Patriae, &amp; Pater Familias,) <hi>To the Governours of Kingdoms, And to the Governours of Families.</hi> JOHN WAGSTAFFE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153724:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s Reſolution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Joſhua 24.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now therefore, fear the Lord, and ſerve him in ſincerity and in truth, and put away the Gods, which your Fathers ſerved on the other ſide of the floud, and in <hi>Egypt;</hi> and ſerve ye the Lord.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Joſhua 24.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And if it ſeem evil unto you to ſerve the Lord, chuſe you this day whom you will ſerve, whether the Gods which your fathers ſerved, that were on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſide of the floud, or the Gods of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> in whoſe land ye dwell: But as for me, and my houſe, we will ſerve the Lord.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Joſhua 24.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the people anſwered and ſaid, God forbid that we ſhould forſake the Lord, to ſerve other Gods; <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Text is too long for a ſingle Sermon, therefore moſtly to enlarge on that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive paſſage; <hi>But as for me, and my houſe, we will ſerve the Lord;</hi> as if he had ſaid, As for others, let them do what they will, the vain obſtinate world do as they think good, but as for his particular part, and his whole houſe, he had undertaken for them, to ſerve the Lord; a rare, but
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153724:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet an excellent Copy ſet before us; therefore let Maſters and their Families endeavour to the utmoſt to tranſcribe it into their practice; to be religious, devout and godly, to ſerve the Lord, the great <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and not the world, themſelves, or the like, which is the beſt way of expreſſing our thankfulneſs for the many Deliverances, that the King and Kingdom has been bleſt withal, by our Homage and Obeyſance to the Soveraign Lord of Heaven and Earth; which does include the ſame to all that are plac'd in Authority under him, our Loyalty and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to them; ſo that obſerve,
<list>
                  <item>1. Here's a Reſolution to be religious and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> not to be wicked, vicious, or factious.</item>
                  <item>2. By whom? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> By one going the way of all the Earth<note n="*" place="margin">Joſ. 23.14.</note>; nay, by a Commander, the Chief General of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Forces, for himſelf, and his Family; not for the Army, or the Nation, or the Country in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, or for any part of it in particular, as the <hi>Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,</hi> or the <hi>Perizzites,</hi> for the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> or <hi>Hittites,</hi> or for the <hi>Gergeſites,</hi> the <hi>Hivites;</hi> or the <hi>Jebuſites,</hi> &amp;c<note n="*" place="margin">Ver. 11.</note>.</item>
                  <item>3. But Thirdly; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> On what was reſolved on; Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, not the Military and War-like, but on the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Service of God.</item>
                  <item>4. To whom in the laſt place? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> To the Lord; not one word of ſerving of ſelf, of Parties, or Factions, of Paſſions, or Prejudices, of Intereſts, by ſiniſter ends, or the like.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I do now expect that you will look for it, that I ſhould inform you in what particulars the Service of the Lord ſhould be expreſt in, thô none be expreſt in the Text. Beſides, the people five or ſix times over in the ſame Chapter confirm the ſame, promiſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153724:5"/>and proteſt to ſerve the Lord<note n="*" place="margin">Ver. 16, 18, 21, 22, 24.</note>, but did not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larize in what; only in general againſt ſinning, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and Idolatry<note n="*" place="margin">Ver. 19, 20.</note>, which we moſtly ought to level our diſpleaſure againſt; at which we will make ſome attempt before we have done. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> But firſt of all to intimate and inſinuate with ſome takingneſs, if it might be, what we ſhould do. And then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſecondly in the Application, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> (without giving any juſt offence) to ſhew you what we have done, and what the very beſt of us all are too ſubject for to do.</p>
            <p>But with the firſt, What we ſhould do as to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of God? All of you know, 'tis well if you did it, that you your ſelves, your ſecond ſelves, your Children, your Servants, ſhould ſerve the Lord; As old Father <hi>Abraham</hi> ſet you long ago a pattern as to himſelf and his houſhold<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 18.19.</note>. And that pious <hi>Joſhua</hi> did the ſame, and that we ſhould do ſo too; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to lay down Precepts, to give them good Rules, but firſt of all, to give them a good Example, and not to reſt there, but take care of them afterwards, to Read to them, to hear them Read, to Catechize (Catechize) inſtruct, to pray with, and for them; to Preach to them, direct them, and the like, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I mean, frequently to mind them of their Duty, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly preſs them to it, and as eagerly to put them on it: But theſe things I ſhall not ſtand to inſiſt on, thô of great conſequence, they are ſo commonly known, yet the Lord knows, too ſeldom practiſed; thô in the New Teſtament you are told, he is worſe than an Infidel that does not take care of his Family and Kindred<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.8.</note>. Now, if proviſion for perſons bodys be ſo neceſſary and reaſonable, what is then due, and of abſolute neceſſity for the good and welfare, for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153724:6"/>the well being, and well doing of our precious long-liv'd Souls, the others being only the ſhells and carkaſſes, at beſt but the Cabinets and Lodgings for theſe, if the breach of the former; if the over-look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Body be ſo cenſur'd and condemn'd for worſe than Heatheniſm, what <hi>(What)</hi> will then the neglect of the other be, the Soul, but termed the higheſt ingratitude, the moſt notorious Crime ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, the moſt capital offence that a man can poſſibly be guilty of, a kind of ſpiritual unnatural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and inhumanity, of butchery and Soul murder, that few, or none would willingly be taxt withal, totally ruining the better part of you and yours, and that for ever, and ever?</p>
            <p>Therefore train up your Children in the way that you would have them to go, and they'l not depart from it when they are old<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 2.6.</note>. And Servants, be not men-pleaſers only, but ſuch as know that you have a Maſter in Heaven, that ſees all, and will firſt or laſt call you unto an Account<note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 6.6, 7, 8.</note>.</p>
            <p>And again, How ſhall a young Man cleanſe his ways, but by taking heed unto God's Word, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accordingly<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 119.9.</note>?</p>
            <p>And laſtly, To you that are Old; 'tis the Lords ſervice only that crowns your gray hairs, and hoary heads with glory<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 16.31.</note>.</p>
            <p>But now you Governours of Families, if you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not by threats, or promiſes, by kindneſſes, or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, reclaim thoſe about you, and under your Roof, or Charge, will it be much amiſs if you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low godly <hi>David</hi>'s practice,<note n="*" place="margin">Verſe 7.</note> as it is in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. not to ſuffer a Lyer, by naming one, I conclude it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends all; a Swearer, a Drunkard, a Fornicator, an Adulterer, no not a Purloiner, a Bate-breeder, a Tale-bearer,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153724:6"/>a Libeller, a State-mender, <hi>that goes out of his own ſphere,</hi> an Evil-doer, to lodge within your doors<note n="*" place="margin">1 Joh. 4.10, 11.</note>, ſo as to countenance or encourage them; but ſuch either reform and change, or, as you have opportunity, to diſmiſs and baniſh out of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and ſociety, company or cuſtody.</p>
            <p>Having now gone ſo far towards the explaining this phraſe of ſerving the Lord, I will further unra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel my meaning.</p>
            <p>Thô 'tis true, one ſays it is this, to be of this Party and Faction, another, 'tis that, to be of that Side and Intereſt; a third declares, it is neither; a fourth cannot tell what it is, is at a loſs, and ſo far to ſeek upon the account of the former, and ſo onwards to many more.</p>
            <p>Now, notwithſtanding all theſe variety of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Opinions, of thwarting, claſhing, and jarringly contradicting one another, it is probable it may ſeem to ſome ſomewhat hard to direct you to keep the Mean and Mid-way amongſt theſe faulty Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams; but (with God's Aſſiſtance) I'le venture to ſtate the caſe, and it may, I hope, pleaſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, or at leaſt all Parties,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.11.</note> the moſt querulous gainſayers ſhall have nothing material to object a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; whilſt I am minding my own buſineſs,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.15.</note> and from the very bottom of my Soul ſtudying to be quiet and peaceable; whilſt I am imploy'd in my Calling<note n="*" place="margin">As ye may ſee in the <hi>Gentleman and Lady's Calling,</hi> Which is worth the frequent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing and practiſing.</note>, for there is none that are, or ſhould be without<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.24.</note>; whilſt I am innocently diverting my ſelf in company; whilſt profitably diſcourſing, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my converſation in Heaven<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 3.20.</note>; whilſt I am boaſting what the Lord hath done for my poor Soul<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 66.16.</note>, that I am not given up to my ſelf, to run with the vile world, to all exceſs of Riot; to be taken with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153724:7"/>the Vanities, Fopperies, Follys of an abuſed Age; how he has reſcued me as a Firebrand out of the Jaws of Death and Hell; whilſt I am inſtructing the Ignorant, reclaiming the Extravagant, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing the Runagate and Prodigal in my Family to return, I am ſerving the Lord; whilſt I am letting them know, what pleaſure I have in being truly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, what ſecret Raptures, raviſhing Tranſports, unknown Paſtimes and Extaſies of Joys I have in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the will of my heavenly Father; it is ſuch a pious Feaſt, and delightful Banquet, that the greateſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curean knows not of<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 14.</note>.</p>
            <p>That I would not be hired off by the wealth of the <hi>Indies,</hi> though a large bribe, to do as I have Done, or to be as vain, ſimple, and fooliſh, as the world, to be as earthly, ſenſual, and Deviliſh, as they that are in it.<note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 3.15.</note> I am ſerving rhe Lord while viſiting the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and Fatherleſs, relieving and comforting of them<note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 1.27.</note>, whilſt reaching out mine hand, and adminiſtring to the neceſſities of the weak, ſick and needy, whether in Soul or body Whilſt I am Sympathizing and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly phancying my ſelf in their deplorable circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and then calling to mind my own happy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; I cannot chuſe but be chearful, Bleſs and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore my God it is not ſo with me, whilſt I am ſetting my hand to the Plow or to the Needle.<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 31.</note> Doing good Offices at home for them; Catering for my ſelf, the family, any body towards clothing the naked, feeding the hungry, nay giving but a Cup of cold water to the thirſty, a poor buſineſs, yet ſufficient If I have no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 10.42.</note>. (Now no Divine or humane Law with us, that I know of, forbids or reſtrains any of us from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any of theſe things.) And laſtly to inſtance in no more, whilſt I am giving a good Example to all that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153724:7"/>are round about me that either converſe with me, know me or hear of me, and do as I would be done by<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 16. Luke 17.10.</note>; and when I have done all<note n="*" place="margin">Col. 3.11.</note> (as if I had done nothing at all) to look for ſalvation through the Merits onely and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of a mighty Saviour and the bleſſed Spirit, and not by my own worthleſs works and ſervices. I am more truly ſerving my God, and doing what he requires of me, then were I with my weak hands, with my feeble power upholding a tottering Ark<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 6.6, 7.</note>; though honeſtly meant, poor <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi>'s life dearly paid for it, or more plainly thus, were I with my ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſupporting a reeling Church unleſs extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily called thereto, which if otherwiſe, 'tis to ſuſpect or Diſtruſt the Lords Ability, and that the Almighty God has need of our poor help.</p>
            <p>But more particularly, whilſt I am Doing the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named things, I am as ſincerely ſerving and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my God, and doing that which is as well pleaſing to him, as if I was hearing a Well compoſed Sermon, that did hit my humour in every <hi>punctillio,</hi> or as if I was in my ſtudy, or cloſet reading a good book, or upon my bended knees Devoutly praying, or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately keeping a voluntary Faſt; thô theſe are excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent things in their places, and muſt by no means be neglected (I Repeat it that I may not be miſtaken, thôugh theſe are excellent things in their places, and muſt by no means be wholly neglected) (and will not be by any Godly Perſon, yet truly the others are the main ones that muſt be done, remembring too that theſe may not be left undone<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 23.23.</note>, for if Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, (are not too diſtaſtful) may but be admitted of. The very Life and Soul, the viſible Effects, and bleſſed fruits the very juice and quinteſcence of all theſe, as of Praying, Reading, Hearing, Faſting, and the like, are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153724:8"/>the former: As it is notably confirm'd in <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy ch. 58. at large, from one end to the other, and let this one place ſuffice for many, becauſe it takes in all others.</p>
            <p>But now to encourage you in ſo noble a ſervice as Serving the Lord, that is an eaſy ſervice firſt<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 11.30.</note>; Not onely eaſy but ſecondly pleaſant<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 3.17.</note>. And 3. Not onely pleaſant,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8.</note> but profitable. And laſtly, Not only profitable, but honourable<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note>. What would any of us deſire more in any ſervice? They are ſuch ſpecial Ingredients, and taking qualifications that would highly recommend to us any Courſe of life beſides. And now what ſtrange ill humour'd Creatures are we that are ſo averſe, and obſtinately bent againſt our own Intereſt, here and happineſs hereafter?</p>
            <p>But to come to the other thing that was promiſed, Application; ſurely 'tis now needleſs, yet for the ſake of the meaneſt I'll make bold with the quickeſt of Apprehenſion as formally to tell you the firſt uſe will be of Exhortation, the next a mild way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, little expreſt, but a great deal to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and the laſt a general and particular Direction or two.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To begin with the uſe of Exhortation, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort us to the ſervice of God, whether of <hi>Paul, Apollo,</hi> or <hi>Cephas</hi> or Chriſt, for I conjecture all theſe kinds and perhaps many more that make up this flouriſhing Congregation; I do not now call you to anſwer to thoſe unhappy unchriſtian-like names, that you have branded each other withall, and as if you delighted in what you have done, taking a kind of a ſecret vaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pride in being ſo termed, paying it off in thinking and forecaſting what you will do<note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 4.</note>. But whatever your private ſentiments may be of the tranſactions of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153724:8"/>world let me prevail with you in this one thing, 'tis no unreaſonable requeſt at all, for then I ſhould not Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to ſpeed,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 3.</note> that we all unanimouſly agree in this to ſerve the Lord [to ſerve the Lord] And in that way too which he himſelf hath appointed, yea in thoſe very things which I have inſtanced in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <p>As for impoſing, or ſo much as glancing on mens Conſciences, they are ſuch nice delicate compoſitions, that they muſt be gently touched, very tenderly dealt withal; 'tis done to my Hands by a more Able Pen called a Diſcourſe on a ſcrupulous conſcience. Therefore to wave that;<note place="margin">By my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Tutor Dr. <hi>Callamy.</hi>
               </note> My Deſign is only to ſtrike at Mens ſinful Actions and practices, and I pray you, ſo forward and encourage me in ſo good a work, sa to bring home the blow. If you will not for Gods ſake, for the Churches, for the Kings, nor for the Kingdoms, nor for Chriſts ſake, nor for your poor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls ſake; yet out of intereſt and advantage, for by &amp; ſiniſter ends, ſerve the Lord. And when once you have taſted how good his Service is,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 34.</note> you will then out of more noble, generous principles, as I hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to you before, it being not only an eaſy, pleaſant, profitable, but an honourable ſervice; ſo that if you love your ſelves, and, who is there that does not? then thirſt after your own real good and happineſs; love God with all your Souls and Minds, and ſerve him with all your ſtrength and might; expreſs it in your Chriſtian Charity, in your hearty love and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to one another, and to love your Neighbour as your ſelf<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam. 2.8.</hi> Non habet cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem Dei qui Eccleſiae non diligit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitatem. <hi>I met with this in that inoffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Learned Author Dr.</hi> Barrow <hi>on Unity.</hi>
               </note>; and as you do expect, and would fain have the like from him, and to the utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for Unity<note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 4.</note>, to be of one mind, ſo great is the advantage of it, but if that is almoſt impoſſible, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153724:9"/>that offences muſt, and will come, as the Saviour of the World informs you<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 17.</note>; but give none, and then you'l be ſure to ſave your own Souls, having chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table thoughts of all, conſtruing every thing in the moſt favourable ſenſe that it is capable of<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.7.</note>; and if there muſt needs be Emulations, and Contentions among you at any time, let them be of the better ſtamp; ſtrive which ſhall out-ſtrip each other in the ways of Piety, and real Holineſs, and frequently of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to overcome one another (which is the beſt ſort of Conqueſt) by abundance of love and condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by frequent acts of kindneſs, and repeated fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, to weary out your very Foes with love, to load them with Gratuities and Courteſies, to do good Offices for bad ones, and the like.</p>
            <p>Thus to perſevere, and hold out to the end, is in good earneſt to ſerve the Lord, our ſelves, our Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, all that we have to do withal, the place we are in, the Neighbourhood, the Country, the King, and the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But in the next place, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> by way of Reprehenſion, to calm it with ſome Advice, and to ſhew you how we have groſly miſtaken the ſervice of God.</p>
            <p>Now if miſerableneſs and covetouſneſs, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> if domeſtick Jars and Diſcords, if little Pikes and Quarrels with our Neighbours, if taking that for ſin which is duty<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note>, if looking upon that to be duty which is none<note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 2.9.</note>; as for Inſtance; If fondneſs to a Party, and diſguſt to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Perſuaſion; if hating and diſdaining; if proud, humility, and phantaſtick conceitedneſs; if throwing our ſelves upon the ground, like a Tennis-ball, with a deſign to rebound ſo much the higher; if baſe Apoſtacy, and downright Revolting; if notorious Hypocriſie, and famous Diſſembling; if this be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153724:9"/>ſerving of God, we have whole ſhoals of ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors to produce daily.</p>
            <p>If diſcontents and murmurings, if whining, and being on the complaining key, if diſobedience and untowardneſs to Superiours, in Office, Age, or Gift, to Parents, Miniſters, Magiſtrates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if burlesquing and buffooning, if miſcalling and nick-naming, if raiſing falſe Reports, and ſpreading them for true ones<note n="*" place="margin">James 3.</note>, if lying and back biting, if blaſting mens Credit, and plundering them of what is more dear to them than their lives, their good Names; if cenſuring, caſting darts and firebrands at one another, as <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs phraſeth it<note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 26.18, 19, 20.</note>; if this be ſerving God, we have enough of this Tribe and counterfeit Stamp to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you withal.</p>
            <p>If ſcandalous Reflections, and boldly ſpeaking evil of Dignities<note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jude.</note>; if inveighing, and letting flie at the Government after a ſtrange rate, and ſaying as it is in the Book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ch. 7. &amp; 10.</note>, What is the cauſe why former times were better than theſe, we do not do wiſely in ſo doing, as that place informs you; yet if all this be ſerving of God, (as 'tis matter of fact,) there's many, too too many do this to ſome pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that do, or ſhould know better.</p>
            <p>And thoſe too that are pleas'd to ſtile themſelves the only true Proteſtant Chriſtians, thô they act clear contrary thereto, they will think me ſurely never the worſe Friend, or greater Enemy<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> for ſpeaking the Truth; but to reprieve your dying Fame, tranſgreſs, ſin no more in this kind, or any other; be no more ſuperſtitious, leſt a worſe thing befall you<note n="*" place="margin">John 5.14.</note> than ever you dreamt of yet, by loſing of both worlds, the preſent <hi>Canaan</hi> in poſſeſſion, and the eternal one in reverſion<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 30.19, 20.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:153724:10"/>
            <p>But again, to direct my Diſcourſe to thoſe, who in their Judgment are for Church-Diſcipline, but in their practice againſt it, which truly does the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt diſſervice, more by far than the moſt enraged of our Enemies. Now if prodigality and intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, if rioting and drunkenneſs, if dallying and fornicating, if curſing and banning, if ſwaggering and ſwearing, hectoring and rallying at thoſe that are not of their Judgment in every nicety and pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctilio (and when did we ever ſee two faces ſo alike, but that they might be diſtinguiſht by a Mole, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a look, or the like?) If this be ſerving of God, there are thoſe that do it with a witneſs, thinking themſelves too the beſt Loyaliſts; but ah poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Souls! 'tis neither to God nor their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that are bad to themſelves, cannot be good to their great Lord and Maſter. <hi>Take away the wicked from before the King</hi> (ſaith King <hi>Solomon</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 16.12, 13, 14, 15.</note>) <hi>and his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſht</hi> (for ever) <hi>in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 25.5.</note> So that it is our ſins that do moſt prejudice our Dread Soveraign, and do undermine his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhake his Kingdom; and unleſs we be truly penitent, 'tis well if we and our moſt glorious King do not periſh<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 12.25.</note>, which the Lord long preſerve Him and all his that are truly Loyal (whatever Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions may be upon their Spirits, to leave that to God and themſelves.) But how can it be imagin'd they that are falſe hearted, treacherous, and diſloyal to their own Souls, that they ſhould be either true or conſtant to God in Heaven, or to Man on Earth? How can it be poſſibly expected, that they that careleſly deſtroy their own lives, ſhould take care of, and charily preſerve Him, His, or any others.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:153724:10"/>
            <p>Therefore inſtead of condemning Providence for being too exact and ſevere with the poor Church of <hi>England,</hi> or with the King or Kingdom at any time. Let's ſtrive to be religious, that's the only way to appeaſe it, to be ſucceſsful and proſperous<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 11.11.</note>, and moſt ſerviceable to all three. 'Tis Righteouſneſs that (that great Politician <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays) exalts a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 14.34.</note>. 'Tis our backſliding and revoltings that is the downfal and overthrow of any people. 'Tis ſin (ſin) that makes breaches in our poor Proteſtant walls, overturns our bulwarks, and moſt fortified places; ſo that I need not apologize to ſuch for my plain deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when calm and ſober as they are. Now, they will ſcarce forgive themſelves, but ſadly bewail, theſe their former miſcarriages, as their imbecillity and weakneſs, as their great frailty, and inexcuſable folly, taking theſe rebukes and buffettings as the higheſt expreſſions of the greateſt friendſhip, and the heartieſt kindneſs<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 9.8. Pro. 27.5, 6.</note>. For every one can act the part of a Sycophant, to ſooth and cajole; but few, or none that of a faithful friend, or true Miniſter of the Goſpel: to blame, reprove, as there is occaſion<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.20, 21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, ſuch knowing that the diſtreſſed Church of <hi>England,</hi> (as to its Doctrine) in her loweſt ebb, will not diſpenſe with ſuch oblique, crooked practices, (this her Sons and Daughters well enough know.)</p>
            <p>If our Practices could but reach our Principles, oh what manner of perſons ſhould we then be in all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converſation and godlineſs! There would then be more difference betwixt them and too many others, as there is betwixt the glorious Sun at noon day in all its bright ſhining luſtre, and the poor Glow-worm that is crawling up the ditch bank, that moſtly ſparkles and glitters in the darkeſt night; this is the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153724:11"/>happineſs of ours, that is by Law enthron'd, I hope ſo firmly fixt, that the Gates of Hell may never prevail againſt it<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note>; though 'tis true, there is none without its ſpots and flaws, yet thoſe that entirely love her, will never ceaſe praying for her peace and welfare<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 122.</note>: But by our ſins, oh my particular friends! we are very unkind, nay cruel to her, that we inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſtab, give the deepeſt wounds to our Religion and Chriſtian Profeſſion<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 2.14.</note>, that are almoſt incurable, by our irregular, unaccountable lives; ſo that for the future, let the innocency of our lives be the Churches beſt Scutcheon, and greateſt glory, the ſweetneſs, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligingneſs of our converſation win upon Proſelite, diſſatisfied Brethren<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 15.2.</note>, Heathens, Runagates, and the like, to gain a Soul, Souls: And if one be of more worth than a world<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 9, 29,</note>, what value ſhall we then put upon thouſands, that will amount to more than ten thouſand Kingdoms or Worlds; therefore let ſuch a ſpirit of Godlineſs, Condeſcenſion, Moderation<note n="*" place="margin">Mal. 16.26.</note>, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Love<note n="*" place="margin">See what the Reverend Biſhop <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſon</hi> ſaith on that ſubject, recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the very much admired Dr. <hi>Tillotſon.</hi>
               </note>, Chriſtian Piety, Honeſty, Charity, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, ſo fill our veins, as to run through all our actions, yea through all the Stages of our life, and ſo brightly ſhine forth upon all the by-ſtanders, as to influence them to do the ſame.</p>
            <p>But again thirdly; If the worſhiping Stocks and Stones, being form'd, hammer'd out into a God, or a Saint, which is no leſs than Idolatry; if perjury or forſwearing, which the Land ought to mourn for<note n="*" place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.9, 10.</note>; if Treaſons or Conſpiracies,<note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 23.</note> which are almoſt as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with ſome as drinking to one another; if Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Maſſacres againſt thoſe that will not be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſame things; if unwearied Plotting and Counter-plotting to help forward a bad Cauſe; if de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of Kings, overturning of Kingdoms, may paſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153724:11"/>for Reformation; if doing theſe things themſelves, when trac'd to the head, yet now and then confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently fathering the ſame on others.</p>
            <p>Now if all this be an Ordinance of God, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God good ſervice, there are thoſe that do it to the life.</p>
            <p>I am not ſo meal mouth'd as to be afraid of naming of them<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 12.4, 5.</note>, but to do Juſtice to a <hi>Jew, Greek,</hi> or a <hi>Turk</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Lev. 19.15.</note>. Thô Popery had got the whip hand of Presbytery,<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 1.17.</note> and was ready to out-top the Reformed Epiſcopacy, which God forbid,<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 24.</note> 
               <hi>(God forbid.)</hi> yet a true Engliſh Chriſtian like Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 10.12, 13.</note>, will ſoon tell you they are the <hi>Roman</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, the Popes Prieſts and Jeſuits, his Vaſſals and Hackney Agents<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 12.9.</note>.</p>
            <p>Or by thoſe that fain would be ſo, or the moſt genuine conſtruction that can be put upon it, that act, and formally do the ſame things, thô they know it not. If this be ſerving of God, there is no doubt but they out-do us all, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their old, Stale State Tenets, Beloved Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, Wedded Politicks, they think they merit Heaven by it, conſecrating the very Inſtruments for ſo holy (or rather horrid) imploy. But the Lord preſerve us from ſo much as being tainted with ſo bloody, blaſphemous, lying, Idolatrous<note n="*" place="margin">Look into Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet</hi>'s works, the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion againſt Idolatry on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the one hand, and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the other.</note>, ſcandalous and tyrannical Religion, that is, for Lording it over mens Conſciences, as well as Lives and Eſtates.</p>
            <p>Now contrary to all theſe, which the Church ſtrictly enjoyns, and which the well conſtituted Laws of the Nation does approve of, and highly recommend to us, and which God himſelf does abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely command, are theſe that follow, which without
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153724:12"/>hyperbolizing, and more gentilely ſtraining, are the beſt &amp; ſtrongeſt Bulwarks to Proteſtaniſm, &amp; the beſt of Religions, if crowned Loyalty, and moſt renowned Fidelity; if upright Honeſty.<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 15.</note>, and unſhaken Piety; if excellent Sobriety, and admirable Charity; if courteous Affability, and friendly Correſpondency; if the deepeſt unfeigned Humility, and bountiful chearful Liberality<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note>; if univerſal Charity, and a true generous Spirit of Chriſtianity,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.</note> is that which paſſes currant with all men for the Service of God, how have all, or at leaſt moſt of us ſwerv'd, warpt, and ſtrangely digreſs'd from it, yea gone a whoring after our own Inventions<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 106.38.</note>?</p>
            <p>Again, if thinking well of every body, and ſpeaking ſo too, ſo far as Truth will bear us out, or otherwiſe to be ſilent<note n="*" place="margin">Titus 3.</note>; for Chriſtian Love will cover a multitude of ſins and miſdemeanours<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.8.</note>. if bearing and forbearing, if real patience and long ſuffering, if forgiving and forgetting, if good turns for bad ones, if ſincerely loving Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies<note n="*" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.15. Matth. 5. Matth. 18.</note>, the Diſſenters, nay the very Papiſts, their Perſons, thô not their Principles, inſtead of down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right hating them; if heartily pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying for their Converſion, inſtead of their Confuſion; if readily bleſſing of them, inſtead of curſing them; and at laſt gaſp with the famous Martyr St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> on our knees to beg of the Lord not to lay it to their charge<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 7.60.</note>; thô at the ſame time they were killing, butchering, and ſtoning of us to death; if this be to ſerve the Lord, as really it is, and that all of you know it too in the higheſt Inſtances; if of Self denial, and Mortification, which far exceeds all Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures, Popiſh Pennances, or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153724:12"/>Pilgrimages to ſeal the Lord's Service with our Blood, which is ſo very precious to us, that we are loth to part with the leaſt drop of it, unleſs it be in the defence and quarrel of our luſts, or for our dearly beloved paſſions; ſo that we may cull out of the thinneſt, or if you pleaſe, out of the fulleſt Congregation, thoſe that are Doers of thy Word, O Lord, and do thus ſerve thee to their lives end, and they would ſcarce be miſt; much more would it be ſo, ſhould we ſearch into For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Countrys, how few, or none, would then be met withal of ſo choice a number? nay, it is well in ſome meaſure, inſtead of meeting with Proſelites, and Profeſſors to Proteſtaniſm, if they were not Rengeadoes, a kind of Heaven Traitors, to ſerve the Lord as Chriſt's own Diſciples did, that inſtead of owning, and boldly confeſſing him, ſneakingly to deſert and forſake him, yea baſely, cowardly to abandon and forſwear him<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 26.70, 72, 74.</note>. Nay, who is there among many, among all theſe that we have taken notice of, that are but devoutly praying and praiſing God,<note place="margin">Luke 6.21.</note> praying to the Almighty to amend and rectifie what is amiſs amongſt us, and at the ſame time to praiſe him<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 2.</note>; that it is no worſe with us, whoſe ſins do ſo abound, ſuperabound, ſo loudly call, cry for vengeance ſpeedily to be executed upon us. He has born long, he will not bear always<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 6.</note>, yet we have not as yet forborn ſinning, but the more incenſt him by our daring Crimes, and repeated Provocations<note n="*" place="margin">1 Joh. 5.19.</note>, as if we would defie Heaven it ſelf to puniſh us; thô he is long lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his hand, yet upon that very account, it will at laſt fall the more heavy upon us.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:153724:13"/>
            <p>If you think this now too high a Charge, it is well if the beſt of us all can come forth, one ſingle perſon, and ſay, that he has done this or the other duty, or abſtain'd from this or the other ſin, ſo as to become a new Man, that was a bad one before, becauſe he ſees God is angry with his People, or the Nation, and threatning them very ſorely; and that a diſmal Cloud is hanging, hovering over our heads by a twined Thred only, that if it be once ſuffered to pour forth its Vials of Wrath and Fury upon us, as if it were Fire and Brimſtone, to humane appearance, it would conſume us, and our poſterity, if not feaſonably prevented by a real Reformation.</p>
            <p>There's no queſtion at all now to be made but many of us would, do, dare talk for our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and, if need were, could fight for God, the Country, the King and Kingdom; but thô we name all theſe, yet it would be with moſt at laſt found, to their laſting diſgrace, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal infamy, that it was moſtly for their near and dear ſelves; for, where are theſe? in what corner of the World are they to be met withal, that would chearfully ſuffer and die for it, that with their Weapons in their hands, could lay them and their Lives at the footſtool of Heaven, and ſay as they profeſs, ſo for to do, daily, thy Will, thy (Will,) not ours, be done? Chriſtianity aſſerts it, I wiſh and pray, that my heart and yours, when it comes to it, may ſay ſo too. For St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> a man of ſufferings, in that known place<note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.12, 13.</note>, tells us poſitively, <hi>All that will live godly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153724:13"/>muſt ſuffer perſecution.</hi> That all of us muſt expect to be buffetted, either in the act, or in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, or in both, as there is occaſion; or as we are call'd to it, but upon no pretence whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to run head-long upon it; yet at laſt how many more will be found Martyrs to their luſts and Phancies, to their unruly humours, and unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward paſſions, than to their God, their Saviour, to their King or Country. You may eaſily ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by what has been already tendred you, I do not at all intend to befriend any Party or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; I had rather my faltering Tongue ſhould cleave to the roof of my Mouth<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 137.</note>, than ſo for to do; my deſign is only to preſs on you uncoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Piety, and real Holineſs, Chriſtian Loyalty, and ready Obedience, whatever comes on't; that I would have you not to be byaſſed, to flag, or be turn'd aſide at any thing, but to weather-beat, and to endure the brunt and ſhock of the moſt threatning dangers<note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 8.6.</note>; for had I ſo much as a thought to become a popular Preacher, to be the Worlds<note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 4.4.</note> Minion or Favourite, and to ſerve my ſelf, inſtead of ſerving my God<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 1.10.</note>, I would go ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way to work<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 82.6, 7.</note>, to keep at as great a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as might be from mens ſins, or ſore pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. As to give you but a taſt<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 24.23.24.</note>, like a fair ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Jeſuit in Maſquerade, that has his full Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to act any part, whether Atheiſt, Fanatick, or Papiſt; that makes nothing at all of wreſting the moſt Sacred Records, ſo as to force them to ſpeak as he would have them; 1. As firſt to one Club rendezvouz of boon Companions, I would comply with them as far as I could; And by my
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153724:14"/>Example I would encourage them to take their ſwing, to eat, drink, play<note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note>, and be merry<note n="*" place="margin">1 Luke 12.9, 20.</note>, and do whatever they had a mind to<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.32.</note>, thô one does not know what a day may bring forth, and that to morrow one may die for't<note n="*" place="margin">Pro, 27.1.</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Again, to another ſelect number and Tribe, I would hearten them on, to take not their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian<note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 1.26.</note>, but the Libertines Liberty, and tell them of luſcious promiſes, fine pleaſing things to tickle their effeminate fancies; and if this did not ſound well, I would in Scripture Language claw their itching Ears,<note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.</note> by crying, Peace, peace; thô ſudden deſtruction was ready to befal them<note n="*" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.3.</note>; yet I would flatter them, that thô they were perverſe and froward, peeviſh and paſſionate, ſelf will'd and head-ſtrong in private, in their Families, if it did not come to the worlds knowledge, I would not boggle, ſeriouſly to tell and tantalize 'em too, that whatever they did, they were God's Jewels<note n="*" place="margin">Mal. 3.17.</note>, the Heirs of Promiſe<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 1.6.</note>, yea the very Darlings of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, thô to their unſpeakable ſorrow, and amazing diſappointment,<note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 5.2.</note> they'd find the bottomleſs Pit to be the only place of their Inheritance,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 23.14.</note> and the Lot and Portion of Hypocrites to be their Doom.<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 24.51.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But again, eſpecially to a third gang and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, that I ſhould expect the greateſt Harveſt from, that ſtile themſelves the moſt Chriſtian-like people, thô the moſt carnal and diabolical<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.</note>, both in their Principles and Practices, I would Saint 'em, and pretend to inroll them in Heavens Calendar, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in hand, as if it did lie in my power to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153724:14"/>ſet them at Chriſt's left and right hand, if they would but unking Kingdoms, and ſet the World it ſelf in a combuſtion<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 17.6.6.</note>, and on a flame, and then would have them with <hi>Pilate,</hi> waſh their hands in innocency<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 27.24.</note>, wipe their mouths too, and ſay, What have they done that ſhould ſo incenſe all Parties againſt them, I would further ſtrive to make them believe that they did God good ſervice thereby<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 16.2.</note>, that they ſhould at laſt have a Coronation, inſtead of meeting with a Damnation day<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note>. If they would but, like the Evil one in the Goſpel<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 13.24, 25, 28.</note>, ſow Weeds and Tares in the Proteſtants Wheat, (not only in private Aſſemblies, but in the Publick ones, that are allowed by Authority,) and when they had done that, to bundle them up Wheat and Chaff, all of us together, eſpecially the moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able oppoſers, as the moſt combuſtible matter, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt for the Papiſts Bonfire, or to take that eaſy plauſible way, as to throw Bones of Contention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and then glory in it<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 3.18.19.</note>, (which ſome I am afraid already have effectually done) making us to bite, tear, devour one another<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 5.14.</note>, without ſo much as putting to their helping hand, and then ſuch ſhall be ſaid to do God good ſervice, thô they were immediately imploy'd in Satan's Drudgery.</p>
            <p>Thus, thus would I do, were I to ſerve my ſelf, or the vain World, thô not ſo bluntly as I have done it here, for this was done deſignedly to let you ſee through the thin Vail that was drawn over a little to diſguiſe &amp; varniſh it dele, ovee but remembring, (remembring,) that I am a Servant of the high God, therefore as Heaven's Ambaſſador, I beſpeak you,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153724:15"/>beſeech you in his moſt glorious Name, having to do with a better Pay-Maſter than ſuch Bragadoſia's, or meer puffs of Wind can pretend to, promiſe me, or any other, do roundly, not mincingly tell you over again by way of general direction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the laſt place; If you do not repent, you ſhall all likewiſe periſh<note n="*" place="margin">Luke. 13.3.</note>. It is not enough that you have <hi>Abraham</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 3.</note>, <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> for your Father; I mean no more by it than this, thô you be born of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Parents, and bear ſo honourable a Name of being Proteſtants, and would continue ſo from one Generation to another, yet that will not ſerve turn, thô you be of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> of <hi>Geneva,</hi> or of the Brotherhood, or of ſeparate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 3. Col. 3.</note>, it will be no acceptable ſervice at all<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.19.</note>, unleſs you do the injoyned Will of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Heaven, be Iſraelites without guile in deed and in truth.</p>
            <p>And that you may be throughly known what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Names you may go by, 'tis demanded from the Church-Party to ſee their Faith by their good works<note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 2.</note>, of all others to know the Tree by its Fruit<note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 7.</note>; this takes moſt, thô both Scripture expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and the ſenſe partly the ſame; the former to ſee their Principles by their Practices, the latter to know their lives by their fruit bearing, I mean, by their upright, honeſt, conſcientious living. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is known for a great truth, to be the Lords Livery, wherever 'tis worn throughout the parts of <hi>Europe, Ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 1.16, 17.</note>. If you'l be ſtil'd the Lord's Servants, a great deal is coucht
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153724:15"/>under thoſe two ſhort Sentences; as to the particulars, I refer you to what hath been already offered to you; but if you would have it over again in other words, look in the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mich. 6.8.</note>; <hi>What does the Lord require of you, but to do Juſtice, love Mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God?</hi> That is in ſhort, let Sobriety and Temperance be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on your ſelves, Righteouſneſs and Juſtice to your Neighbour, Piety and Godlineſs to your Maker, and you will find<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 13.13.</note>, that you are not then to be found in Rioting and Drunkenneſs, not in Chambering and Wantonneſs, not in Strife and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but imitate the Lord Jeſus, as he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready given us an Example.</p>
            <p>I can only now touch on things, and as it were, dart Truths at random; yet as you have it in the firſt Book of <hi>Samuel</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 17.</note>, a ſtone being ſlung by a contemptible Stripling, what effect it had. Now God's Spirit, and your own Conſcience levelling this and the other Truth, that it may hit the white, the mark, ſink down into the heart, and kill a <hi>Goliah,</hi> a Gigantick ſin, whatever you may tearm me for throwing my poor Mite into the Treaſury and Corban of the Lord's Service.<note n="*" place="margin">Mark 12.</note> I'le not go on in reparteeing as to call you uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed Chriſtians, whilſt I am upon ſerving <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s living God, but accoſt you with all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and tenderneſs that the Subject is able to bear. I'le treat you, yea addreſs my ſelf to you, not as you are the poor deſpicable Subjects of a great Prince, but as if ye were ſo many Grandees and Monarchs of ſeveral little Worlds and Countrys,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153724:16"/>which was the firſt Original of Families, as you may ſee at large in the Old Teſtament; every Head of a Family, being a kind of a petty God or King; and ſtill in many reſpects you are ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Precincts and Provinces, within your own proper Stations and Boundaries, within your own Dominions and Domeſtick Territories, if you do not forfeit your right and title thereto by a falſe Religion, by Rebellion, Sacriledge, or the like, which is cry'd out againſt as much as the deadly ſin of Sorcery or Witchcraft<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 15.23.</note>.</p>
            <p>Therefore 'tis to you pious Parents, and worthy Governours of your Families, thô you have never ſo mean thoughts of your ſelves, the more you are ſo for being humble, meek, lowly, and ſubmiſſive, that my ſuit is in the behalf of the great Majeſty, not only of Earth, but Heaven, that you and your houſes would reſolve<note n="*" place="margin">In what manner Dr. <hi>Calamy</hi> has done't, you may ſee on that Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. pag. 28, 29, 30, 31. 'tis with that confeſſion, ſolemnity, proteſtation, &amp; noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſpirit, that it deſerves to be ingrav'd in Letters of Gold, if it would but excite all others to take up the ſame Chriſtian alike reſolution in the behalf of God, the Church, the King, the preſent Government, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, againſt either Popery or Fanaticiſm.</note> to ſerve the Lord; There <hi>(There)</hi> there you are ſo many petty Kings to controul and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand according to your own private will and pleaſure, and your dutiful Children are as ſo many little Princes about you, and your truſty Servants are as ſo many Lords, not Slaves, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on you. Now is it not great pity that ſuch a glorious Equipage, heavenly Retinue, ſhould be badly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in Satans drudgery inſtead of the Lords ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable ſervice; yea every poor man in his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-beaten Cottage, has as much Command and Authority there under his thatcht Roof, and narrow
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153724:16"/>Confines, as the Peer and Noble man has within his ſpacious Mannor, or Princely Pallace.</p>
            <p>Therefore all of you, I humbly beſeech you, Rule well within your own Stations and Territories, keep up their good Order and Kingly Government, and inſtruct all under you, in Obedience and Duty, in Juſtice and Honeſty, to your ſelves, and others; and what you expect from them, to you, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that golden Rule, Doing as you would be done by; it does not repent me, thô this be the ſecond or third time: I have had it on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that you by your Examples preſs it the more on them, by doing it, and continually practiſing the ſame, your ſelves to thoſe above you; eſpecially to thoſe to whom you owe ſubjection, to Kings and to all that are plac'd in Authority under them, and then this will be to the honour of God, to the Advancement of your Religion, to the Well being of your ſelves, to the promoting of your Families, to the Benefit of your Neighbours, to the Glory of our Nation, and at laſt to your own Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And till you have done all this in your own houſes, be not under any pretence whatſoever drawn out to the reforming, and new-modelling of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: It is too great a work for every Mechanick or ſingle States-man to undertake, ſuch grand matters are for the whole Nation to conſult on, or at leaſt for their Repreſentatives imbodyed into one; For what ſays the wiſe man, that great States man of all others, King <hi>Solomon</hi> by name, That <hi>in the multitude of Counſellors there is (much) ſafety</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 11.14.</note>. So that now for you that are preſent, thô many, yet ſcarce the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153724:17"/>Man of them that are in His Majeſties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion: Therefore it behoves you, inſtead of mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and new molding of Kingdoms, let your Eyes be turned within doors; begin at home, and you will find ſuch need of repairs there, that you'l not eaſily be tempted to look abroad for want of better Imployment, as the Lord knows all of us too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently are. Grant that the Nation is bad, very bad, but do not you make it worſe by being ſo too. Nay further, admit of it, that it not only has a Mote, but a very great Beam in its Eye, that it is not at all ſenſible of it, and almoſt blinded with it, that it begins to be frantick and raving, with its pricking pain; what then, ſhall we like Quacks and Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks, long to be medling and tampering with it? No, no! I hope we are all of us ſo ingenuous, and I do not at all doubt of it, but that we will free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledg that there is ſomething, thô it be never ſo little in our own Eyes, that each ſingle perſon in the Kingdom would be pleas'd to pluck out that which is in their own, or in their Families; and when we come to ſee clearly, by that time there will not be ſo much as the leaſt Speck, Iota, in the Eye of the Nation left.</p>
            <p>To conclude; We have hitherto been too prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterouſly imploy'd, and begun undiſcreetly, very odly at the wrong end, as if we would Tile the Houſe, or Thatch it with Straw or Stubble, and then daub up the Walls with our untemper'd Mortar, and not only ſo, but to hang it too in the fleeting Air by Geometry, before we have ſo much as laid the very foundation, the firſt corner Stone. The
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153724:17"/>New Teſtament tells you, this is not like a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-builder<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 14.</note>. We may hold up theſe light ſhingles, or whiffling ſtraws, that the wind blows to and fro up in our hands, or ſupport them for a ſhort time, with the ſtrong blaſts of our foul mouths, but in time weary of the Imploy, and ſlaviſh Service, they will at laſt, (if not timely taken down,) fall like heavy Slates, upon our heads, and daſh us, ours, our Religion, our threatned Church, our tottering State, our poor King, and poorer Kingdom, into a thouſand piece-meals<note n="*" place="margin">Nahum.</note>, making all our Habitations <hi>empty, void and waſte,</hi> which the Lord in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy prevent, and grant that we and our Houſes may forth with ſerve the Lord, in that manner that may be moſt acceptable to him, that he, and his Church, has appointed, to his Glory, and to our own Salvation: The Lord grant ſo great a bleſſing to the whole Nation, for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153724:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
